Welcome to Colab.
콜랍에 잘 오셨어요
Welcome to the week seven day two Colab.
콜랍 일주일째입니다 이틀째죠
And just before we try our base model, we're going to actually see these tokenizers in action.
기본 모델을 시도하기 전에 토큰라이저가 작동하는 걸 볼 수 있어요
Uh, start with some Pip installs and some imports as usual.
평소처럼 Pip 설치와 외부에서 작업하세요
And now in the constants section, I'm going to set up four different tokenizers that we will just quickly
이제 상수 섹션에서 4개의 다른 토큰라이저를 설정하겠습니다 잠깐 살펴보죠
After that, we're going to look at our base model llama and do some some work with the data.
그 다음에는 베이스 모델 라마를 보고 데이터로 작업을 좀 할 거예요
And I've also got the constants here for writing to the output in color that you may remember from when
그리고 색상 출력에 작성을 위한 상수도 있어요 과거에 결과를 시각화할 때 기억하실지도
we visualized results in the past.
모르겠네요
All right, let's run that.
좋아요, 실행해 보죠
We log in to hugging face using the usual snippet that you know well at this point.
얼굴을 껴안는 데 로그인합니다 여러분이 잘 아는 일반적인 스닙 조각으로요
And now I've written a useful function called investigate tokenizer that takes a model name.
그래서 모델 이름을 가진 토큰라이저 조사하기라는 유용한 함수를 만들었어요
And what that does is it uh, will load in the tokenizer for that model name, and it will then iterate
그러면 모델 이름을 위한 토큰라이저를 로드하고 이 6개의 숫자를 반복합니다
through these six numbers zero, one, ten, 100, 999, and 1000.
0, 1, 10 100, 999, 1000이죠
For each of those numbers, it will convert it into a string, and then ask the tokenizer to convert
각각의 숫자에 대해 문자열로 변환합니다 그런 다음 토큰라이저에게 그 문자열을 토큰으로
that string into tokens.
변환하라고 하죠
So what are the tokens that represent the string 100 as a piece of text?
문자열 100을 텍스트로 나타내는 토큰은 무엇일까요?
Um, and I'm using this add special tokens as false parameter.
이 특별한 추가 토큰을 가짜 매개 변수로 사용하고 있어요
What that means is please don't add in things like a start of sentence token and an end of sentence
문장의 시작 토큰과 끝 토큰 같은 것을 추가해서 다른
token or something like that that will interfere with things.
것을 방해하지 말라는 뜻이죠
Just simply convert this text into tokens that represents that text.
단순히 이 텍스트를 해당 텍스트를 나타내는 토큰으로 변환하세요
Um, so that's what it will do.
그게 이 기계의 역할이죠
And then it will print that out.
그럼 그걸 프린트하죠
So to run that and to show it let me call investigate tokenizer.
실행해서 보여드리기 위해 토큰라이저를 조사할게요
And we will start by calling it for the llama three one uh model.
라마 3 모델로 시작하도록 하죠
And let's see what we get.
Get in get을 해 보죠
So what we get is the string zero.
문자열 0이 나오죠 get
Text zero converts to the token number 15.
텍스트 0은 토큰 넘버 15로 변환되죠
One goes to the token 16.
하나는 16번 토큰으로 가요
Ten goes to token number 605.
10은 605번 토큰에 있어요
As it happens.
공교롭게도요
And you'll see that similarly 109.99 they each mapped to a single token.
109도 비슷하게 생겼고요 99개씩 토큰 하나에 매핑됐어요
1000 though that maps now to two tokens.
1,000달러면 토큰 2개와 같아요
In fact, it maps to the token for the number 100.
숫자 100의 토큰과 매핑이 되죠
If you see that followed by the token for the number zero and that.
0과 다른 숫자가 적힌 토큰이 보이시죠?
So just just as you would imagine, it is the tokens for the text 100, followed by the text for a zero.
여러분이 상상하시는 것처럼 텍스트 100의 토큰과 0의 텍스트죠
And what you see here, loud and clear, is that if we're just focusing on three digit text numbers,
여기서 명확하게 볼 수 있듯이 3자리 숫자에만 초점을 맞춘다면
on three digit numbers, we have this useful property that whatever price we have is always going to
어떤 값을 가지고 있든 토큰 하나에 대응할 수 있는 유용한 속성이
map to one token.
생기죠
So the model's task of trying to predict the price of a product will end up being just predict one token
즉 제품의 가격을 예측하는 모델의 작업은 결국 토큰 하나를 예측해서 올바른 토큰을 얻는 것이 됩니다.
and get that token right, and then you've got the right price of the product.
그렇게 되면 제품의 가격이 올바른 것이죠.
Um, and so it's not an essential property.
그래서 필수적인 자산이 아니에요
We don't require that these models are perfectly able to generate a sequence of tokens, but it's convenient
이 모델들이 토큰의 배열을 생성할 수 있어야 하는 것은 아니지만 이 토큰 하나만 제대로
that we're going to simplify the problem down to just getting this one token right.
만들어도 문제를 간단하게 해결할 수 있어서 편리하죠
And we can also see how this looks for another model like K-125.
K-125 같은 다른 모델도 이렇게 생겼는지 알 수 있죠
Uh, and now we see something different.
이제 다른 게 보여요
The single digits zero and one mapped to a single token, but ten maps to two tokens.
0과 1은 토큰 하나에 매핑되지만 10은 토큰 2개에 매핑되죠
In fact, the token for one followed by zero 100 is 100999 is presumably 999, and 1000 is 1000, uh,
1에 대한 토큰과 0, 100을 합치면 100999고 999이고 1,000은 1,000이죠 거기서 사용된
for tokens being used there.
토큰의 값이에요
So you see that different property.
다른 속성을 볼 수 있죠
And hopefully that really clarifies, um, why I think llama three one has an edge.
라마31이 왜 유리한지 이번 일로 명확해졌으면 좋겠어요
Uh.
네
Gemma.
제마요
Two for Gemma, two.
제마는 두 개예요
Sorry.
미안해요
Uh, Gemma.
제마요
Two similar properties to Kwon.
권 회장과 비슷한 두 가지 특성이 있어요
Uh, interestingly, uh, totally different vocabulary.
흥미롭게도 완전히 다른 어휘예요
It's a much bigger number, but that's no surprise.
훨씬 큰 숫자지만 놀랍진 않아요
There's no reason why they should have the same vocabulary.
같은 단어를 쓸 이유가 없죠
Um, and, um.
음, 음요
Yeah, it's, uh, clearly, uh, not not a one token for for one three digit number.
네, 토큰이 하나가 아니라 세 자리 숫자네요
Um, and Phi three is, as I say, similar.
피3도 아까 말했듯이 비슷해요
Uh, there is actually a different variant of phi three, a smaller variant that has the same nice properties
사실 파이3에도 다른 변종이 있어요 라마가 가진 더 작은 변종이지만 라마의 3-1과 같은 멋진 특성을
as Lama three one.
갖고 있죠
So that is another thing that would be worth potentially trying.
그것도 시도해 볼 만한 가치가 있어요
Um, as could any of these be tried?
이 중 어떤 것도 시도할 수 없었겠죠?
It's not a disqualifier that that it produces multiple tokens by any means.
여러 패를 만든다고 해서 자격이 없는 건 아니에요
All right.
좋아요
Well, anyway, that gives you a background to the tokenizers and a good sense for why we picked the
자, 이제 토큰라이저에 대해 알아봤고 왜 그 모델을 선택했는지도
model that we did.
알게 되었네요
Uh, in the next video, we will then load in data and try testing our model.
다음 영상에서는 데이터를 불러와서 모델을 테스트해 볼게요